Okay בוקר טוב boker tov everybody. Today's דף daf is
דף נ"א daf nun alef and we pick up on the two
dots, four lines from the top, and we are now moving on
to the next part of the משנה. mishna. We dealt with the
issue that a husband does not have חזקה hazaka in his wife's
property because he has a right to eat and even if he
waived the right, we assume the wife doesn't mind and then we
even had a interesting debate about whether anybody has a חזקה hazaka
in a wife's property since she says she was relying on her
husband. And now we go to the flip side of that, which
is, does a woman have חזקה hazaka in her husband's property? So
that's the next line in the משנה: mishna: ולא לאשה חזקה בנכסי
בעלה. V'lo l'ishah chazakah b'nichsei ba'alah.
A woman does not have חזקה hazaka in her husband's property. Now
to us that would not be obvious, why should a woman have
rights in her husband's property to be like, you know, eating the
fruit of the field? Again, maybe we could say she's not מקפיד,
makpid, he's not מקפיד, makpid, you know, it's his wife, but she
doesn't have legal rights, but let's see what the גמרא Gemara says
to that. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, isn't this obvious?
כיון דאית לה מזוני מזוני הוא דקאכלה. Keivan d'is lah mezonoi mezonoi
hu d'ka'achla. He has a responsibility to provide for her food, to
provide sustenance for her. So therefore that's right, his one of his
obligations of the כתובה. ktubah. We discussed this the other day, that
he gets her מעשה ידיה, ma'aseh yadayim, he gets her earnings, and
in exchange, or the primary part of that was חז"ל Chazal wanted
to make sure that she was provided for, that she had lodging
and
board and what
they call room and board. Room and board, there you go. Room
and board. So we should assume
that that's מזונות. mezonos. So we should assume
that her taking of the fruit is part of his financial obligations
to her, not
necessarily took the form of him saying, go out to the field
and harvest the fruit, but since he has financial obligations to her
on an ongoing basis, we should assume that this is part of
that. So obviously in that
context we should not interpret this as חזקה. hazaka. So the גמרא
Gemara says לא צריכא דייחד לה ארעא אחריתי למזונה. lo tzricha d'yached
lah ara achrita l'mezonah. No, no, no. The case would be similar
to before, that this is clearly not her legal right. He has
designated a different field. He has said you're going to get my
obligation to provide for you food and whatever daily provisions, that's going
to be from that field over there, that field to the north
of my lands, and she's eating the fruit from the south of
the land. So clearly it's not based on his ongoing financial obligations
to her, but nevertheless, because of their marriage, we assume that he's
not מקפיד makpid when she eats from his field and therefore it
is not a חזקה hazaka even if she's doing it for an
ongoing basis for three years. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says,
and as it did before when it was dealing with the reverse
case, there's no חזקה. hazaka. So the גמרא Gemara says
שמע מינה, sh'ma mina, can we infer from this המוכר שדה לאשתו
קנתה. hamocheir sadeh l'ishto kanah. Sorry, I skipped a line. הא ראיה
יש. Ha raya yesh. So there's no חזקה, hazaka, but if she
actually produced a שטר star that he sold it to her, it
would be good. Okay, that should be obvious. Not necessarily. לימא לגלויי
זוזי הוא דבעי. leima l'igluyei zuzei hu d'ba'ei. Let's say that we
should interpret a sale, a man when a man sells to his
wife, we shouldn't interpret it as a real sale. We should say
it's all a ruse, it's all a device in order to make
sure that he can find out if she's hiding any money from
him.
Alright, so even though he went through these motions and signed a
שטר star and said he was selling it to her, he really
never intended to sell it to her, he really only tried to
find money she might be hiding away from him, presumably with the
presumption that he's really entitled to that money. Now again, if she
brings money into the marriage and it's not written into the
כתובה, ktubah, then it's her money, she never gives up title. He
maybe has a right to be אוכל פירות, ochel perot, so maybe
he's trying to find that money and he wants to make sure
that she didn't hide away money before the marriage and that's money
that he should be entitled to the earnings off of that money.
Or maybe it's money that she got during the marriage and then
we have a general principle that מה שקנתה אשה קנה בעלה. mah
shekanas ishah kanah ba'alah. So maybe he's afraid that somebody gave her
money, maybe she earned money at a job, right, and her מעשה
ידיה ma'aseh yadayim is his, and she's hiding it away in some
hidden bank account, and he's entitled to it, and he wants to
find it. So given all of that, we will be inclined to
interpret it that way. And again, part of this is informed by
the fact that we understand that as a general rule a husband
would have rights to his wife's money. So therefore as soon as
we say that he sold her land, maybe the first thing that
occurs to us, wait, he sold her land, where'd she get that
money from, whose money is that? So given that, you know, let's
maybe be inclined to interpret it as not a real sale and
a way for him to identify
money she's hiding that he really has rights to. So why don't
we say that? So the גמרא Gemara says... Now, so should we
say that from the implication of our משנה Mishnah that חזקה Chazakah
there isn't, but a שטר ראיה Shtar Reayah there is, that maybe
that case would be, that that would tell us that we don't
say that, that we treat a sale as a real
sale? ושמע מינה U-shma mina should we infer from this המוכר שדה
לאשתו קנתה hamocher sadeh le-ishto kanta that if a man sells a
field to his wife we should say that she actually genuinely takes
possession of it, ולא אמרינן לגלויי זוזי הוא דבעי ve-lo amrinan l'gluyei
zuzei hu d'baei and we don't say that he's just doing it
as a way to uncover any money she might be hiding away?
So is that implied? So the גמרא Gemara says לא, Lo, not
necessarily. Maybe yes, maybe no, but you can't prove it. אימא הראיה
יש, Eima ha-reayah yesh, it's true our משנה Mishnah implies that there
is a ראיה, reayah, that there would a שטר shtar that would
be valid. But what type of a שטר shtar would be valid?
בשטר מתנה, Bishtar matanah, if it was a שטר shtar of a
gift where she would not be producing any money, then that would
be valid. So certain שטרות shtarot that show she owns it would
be valid. But maybe a שטר מכר, shtar mecher, we should say
the whole thing is a ruse, and therefore we would invalidate that
שטר shtar because it's a way for him to find money that
he's entitled to. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, now again, that's
quite striking, but I want to remind you that we said the
same thing the other day in the opposite direction. That maybe, you
know, when she sells him a field, we should assume that it's
not a good sale because she's only doing it to make her
husband, you know, so that her husband isn't angry at her. So
in the context of a marriage, how do we interpret these types
of sales and what really is going on? You know, we bring
a very different lens to it. And it's not necessarily to favor
one side or favor the other side. So in her case we
might say if she's selling something she's pressured by her husband to
sell it. In his case we could say, look, you know, in
general, why does he need his... why does he need to sell
something to his wife? Isn't he entitled to that money? So maybe
it's only... he's not really selling it, he's only doing it to
find money she's hiding. Now of course you might think well maybe
it makes a difference how obvious it is that that money was
hidden or not hidden. Like let's say they signed a prenup and
she really did come in with her own assets, and she signed
a prenup and said, you know, all of these... you know, all
the money in this bank account and in these investments is only
mine and I have title to it and you don't have אכילת
פירות achilat peirot over that money etc. And that was money that
was well known to be hers. And then he sells her a
field, and from that money, and she pays for it from that
money. Therefore, in that case, obviously it would be a good sale.
But in other cases, in a סתם stam case, let's assume that,
you know, he should have rights to her money and if he
doesn't, maybe that's what's going on here for her to... him to
find out it's hidden money. So the גמרא Gemara says maybe that's
true, and maybe therefore the only type of a שטר shtar that
would be good would be a שטר מתנה, shtar matanah, a gift
and not a sale. So now we're going to focus on... we're
going to hear different opinions about this הלכה. halachah. אמר ליה רב
נחמן לרב הונא, Amar lei Rav Nachman l'Rav Huna, רב נחמן Rav
Nachman says to רב הונא, Rav Huna,
לא הוית מר גבן באורתא בתחומא. lo haveit mar gaban be-orta bi-tchuma.
The master, you, רב הונא, Rav Huna, you weren't with us last
night in the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. תחומא, Tchuma, the reason תחומא
tchuma is called the בית מדרש Beis Medrash is, the רשב"ם Rashbam
says, you know, their בתי מדרשות Batei Midrashot were out in the
fields, and he even says maybe the reason they were out in
the fields was to make them in a location that was within
the תחום tchum of the surrounding villages so people could come on
שבת. Shabbos.
But anyway, you weren't with us last night in the בית מדרש,
Beis Medrash, דאמרינן מילי מעלייתא. d'amrinan milei ma'alyata. We said such a
good idea, we had such a good discussion and we came up
with such a good פסק psak last night and too bad you
weren't there. Okay, so he says אמר ליה מאי מילי מעלייתא? amar
lei mai milei ma'alyata? Oh, what was that good thing you said?
סו אמריתו, So amrisu, so
he says, we said המוכר שדה לאשתו קנתה hamocher sadeh le-ishto kanta
that if a man sells a field to his wife she does
purchase it, it is a good sale, ולא אמרינן לגלויי זוזי הוא
דבעי ve-lo amrinan l'gluyei zuzei hu d'baei and we don't say that
he's just trying to do it to get hold of her assets.
Okay, we would take the document on face value and it's a
sale and that's the end of the story and she had money
that he didn't have rights to, end of story. So the גמרא
Gemara says אמר ליה פשיטא amar lei pshita obviously. You know that
you tell somebody oh you missed a great thing and then you
tell them the great thing, ah I didn't need to know that,
that was obvious. פשיטא, Pshita, isn't that obvious? Now why is that
obvious? דלו זוזי מהכא ותקני לה בשטרא. dalu zuzei mehacha ve-tiknei lah
bi-shtara. So even without the money, the שטר, shtar, if it was
a sale that was both a transfer of money and a writing
of a שטר, shtar, so the שטר shtar itself would have transferred
the field even if there wasn't money. מי לא תנן Mi lo
tnan did we not teach in the משנה Mishnah
נכסים שיש להם אחריות נקנים בכסף בשטר ובחזקה nechasim she-yeish lahem achrayut
niknim be-chesef bi-shtar u-ve-chazakah that things that do... I'm sorry,
נכסים שיש להם אחריות, nechasim she-yeish lahem achrayut, excuse me, you know,
property that has liens on it that could theoretically have liens, meaning
fields, real estate, are transferred with כסף kesef with money, with a
שטר shtar with a document, and with an act of חזקה, chazakah,
not our חזקה, chazakah, a different חזקה, chazakah, taking... you know, doing
something to... to improve the field. Now why is this relevant? Who
cares if it's transferred with a שטר shtar or with a money?
The bottom line is is that the whole thing was a ruse.
He's doing it in order to find money he's entitled to. to
find access to her money. So what if there is a—why should
the fact that in theory one of those can work as a
קנין kinyan without the other, why should that be relevant? So the
way תוספות Tosafot explains it is it depends on the order.
Assuming that the order was, and I don't know why we should
assume that this was the order, but assuming that the order was,
at first she handed over the money and then after she handed
over the money he wrote a שטר shtar to her. In that
case the point is clearly he wasn't just doing this as a
ruse. Because if he was just doing this as a ruse and
all you had was the money you could say fine that money
wasn't a sale and he was just doing it to get access
to the money. But if afterwards he wrote a שטר, shtar, then
why is he writing a שטר shtar once he's got that money
in his hands? It must be that it's a good sale. And
even if I were to grant you that the money was just
to get access to the money, the fact that he followed it
by a שטר, shtar, that שטר shtar is itself a transfer of
the land. So let's assume that that money wasn't serious, it wasn't
a sale, he was just getting access to her funds. But the
שטר shtar is a sale, end of story. Okay, so that makes
a lot of sense if that's the order. But you understand that
if the order is the opposite it doesn't make sense, because he
wanted access to the funds and the only way she was going
to hand over the money was once he wrote the שטר. shtar.
So the writing of the שטר shtar obviously doesn't do anything because
it was only a way to get access to the funds. But
if the money changed hands first and then the שטר, shtar, then
of course that makes a lot of sense. Okay, so that's what
he said. Who needs that חידוש? chiddush? You have the שטר shtar
that came after the money changed hands. So דאזיל המנונא ודיקנא בשטרא,
de'azil Hamnuna vedikna beshtara, the שטר shtar should work. ולא תנן, velo
tenan, did we not teach, נכסים שיש להם אחריות נקנים בכסף בשטר
ובחזקה. nechasim sheyesh lahem achrayot niknim bechesef beshtar uvechazakah. אמר ליה, amar
lei,
so he said back no you still needed our חידוש. chiddush. A
שטר shtar wouldn't have been enough. Why? ולאו איתמר עלה velav itmar
alah אמר שמואל amar Shmuel לא שנו אלא בשטר מתנה. lo shanu
ela beshtar matanah.
When is it that a שטר shtar is enough to effect the
transfer? If it explicitly is a gift. אבל בשטר מכר לא קנה
עד שייתן דמים. aval beshtar mecher lo kanah ad sheyiten damim. But
if it's a שטר shtar of sale, the שטר shtar doesn't work
without the money. So therefore you need that money to really have
been the money that was the payment for the field. So you're
saying even if that money was him just to get access, the
שטר shtar that came afterwards worked. And is that true? If you
say the money was just to get access, so the field was
never paid for. And if the field was never paid for and
the שטר shtar is presenting itself as a שטר מכירה, shtar mechira,
then the שטר shtar is not effective without the money. And therefore
you need to say for this sale to be good that not
only did you have a שטר, shtar, but as a שטר מכר,
shtar mecher, the money was a real purchase money and was not
just him to get access to the money. So therefore, meaning they're
not disagreeing, they're both saying it's a good sale. But one is
saying you don't need this חידוש chiddush like that he's not trying
to get access to the funds. That would be true even if
he were trying to get access to the funds. And the answer
is no. If he were only trying to get access to the
funds then it would not be a good sale because then the
money would not have been legitimate payment and the שטר shtar would
not have worked without the money. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues.
Okay,
and we're still going to argue whether the שטר shtar would work
without the money. So you're saying that שמואל Shmuel says that a
שטר מכר shtar mecher needs money. So ולאו מותיב רב המנונא, velav
motiv Rav Hamnuna, but one minute רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna challenged that.
How could you say that a שטר מכר shtar mecher does not
work by itself without the money? בשטר כיצד, beshtar keitzad, we got
a משנה Mishna that says how do you transfer a field with
a שטר? shtar? כתב לו על הנייר או על החרס, katav lo
al haniyar o al hacheres, if somebody writes on a piece of
paper or even a piece of pottery, אף על פי שאין בו
שווה פרוטה, af al pi she'ein bo shaveh perutah, even if it's
not even worth a cent this piece of property—this piece of excuse
me paper, pottery, or the piece of
paper. שדי מכורה לך שדי נתונה לך sadi mechurah lach sadi netunah
lach or נתונה לך netunah lach might have been the phrase. הרי
זו מכורה ונתונה. harei zu mechurah unetunah.
It works. So it seems very clear that a שטר shtar works
without money, even a שטר מכר. shtar mecher. Okay, so how could
שמואל Shmuel say a שטר מכר shtar mecher only works with the
money? Here it sounds that a שטר shtar works, even just a
simple writing on a simple piece of paper, even a little piece
of pottery is going to work. So again if we reject שמואל,
Shmuel, a שטר מכר shtar mecher does not need money, a שטר
מכר shtar mecher works by the שטר shtar itself. And therefore I
really don't care what you say the purpose of the money was,
the שטר shtar should work by itself. So the גמרא Gemara says
ולאו הוא מותיב לה והוא מפרק לה. velav hu motiv lah vehu
mefareik lah. But one minute, but the same רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna
who challenged שמואל Shmuel based on this statement also said you know
what? This משנה Mishna that says that you can just write a
little on a piece of paper that you're selling something and it
doesn't need money, that doesn't really disprove שמואל. Shmuel. Really it might
be that a שטר מכר shtar mecher really does need the money.
So how does it not disprove שמואל? Shmuel? He suggested the answer
himself. himself. במוכר שדהו מפני רעתה. B'mocha sadei mipnei ra'asa. That would
only be that a שטר מכר shtar mecher doesn't need money if
somebody is trying to offload a bad piece of property. Okay, and
in that type of a case, we assume that the person is
so eager to finalize the sale that he will do it with
a שטר מכר, shtar mecher, that he will do it even before
he's received the payment. What this shows you is again, and this
is true even today I think, about how important real estate is
to people in terms of an
asset. But certainly there when people were not fundamentally in this business
as for commercial purposes, buying and selling and so on, it was—you
were really talking about their estates and the fields that they inherited
that are going to stay with their family, that there was a
lot of resistance and inertia against selling your real estate. So therefore
we would say if you're really selling—in a normal case you're selling
a piece of property, you're not really finalize that sale in your
mind even if you wrote a שטר shtar until you received the
cash. That's what שמואל Shmuel says. The שטר shtar is not valid
until you've received the cash. But if you've got a lousy piece
of property and you're trying to offload it, then once you do
any מעשה קנין, ma'aseh kinyan, even just a שטר, shtar, even without
being paid for it, it's final. So that statement that it works
is only a field you're trying to offload. So given that, we
come back to our full circle. So if you say that שמואל
Shmuel is correct that a שטר מכר shtar mecher only works with
the payment money, then you have to say that that payment money
was real payment money. And you had that we're not going to
assume that the husband was just doing it to get access to
the funds. Because if he was just getting access to the funds
and it wasn't real payment money, at least from his perspective, then
the שטר shtar would not have been enough because we're going to
affirm שמואל Shmuel that a שטר מכר shtar mecher needs the money
to change hands. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says here's another
explanation, by the way, about this סתימתא דאורייתא דאנתונה sitima de-orsita de-antunah
to affirm שמואל. Shmuel. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, and רב
אשי Rav Ashi also adds, במתנה ביקש ליתנה לה. be-matanah bikesh litna
lah. No, no, no. We're going to read even when he says
שדי מכורה לך sadi mekhura lakh under some cases—the question is which
cases—that it works not as a
שטר מכר. shtar mecher. A שטר מכר shtar mecher really would need
the money to change hands, like we're saying by the case of
the husband and wife. What about this teaching that it works
to write on a piece of paper, "I'm selling you my field,"
and it doesn't need the money to change hands? When you're really
trying to give it as a מתנה. matanah. ולמה כתב לה בלשון
מכר? Ve-lamah katav lah bi-leshon mecher? So then why did you write
"I'm selling it to you"? כדי ליפות כחו, Kedei le-yafos kocho, in
order to give him greater rights to the field. How does somebody
who receives a field as a מכר mecher have a greater right
than rather than having received it as a מתנה? matanah? So the
most obvious difference is if somebody comes, if a creditor comes and
takes possession of that field, right? He takes it in payment of
a debt. So if I just got the field as a מתנה,
matanah, I can't go back to the guy and say, "Hey, a
creditor of yours took it, reimburse me." Now, by the way, it
is possible that even when somebody gives a מתנה, matanah, he gives
a מתנה matanah with insurance. But under a normal case, I would
not have a right to demand him to reimburse me. Whereas if
I bought the field and a creditor took it, I could go
ahead and say, "Hey, you've got to reimburse me," or even if
he doesn't have a legal right to reimburse me, I could still
say, "You know, you have to make it good, you have to
do something
to appease me here because I paid good money for it and
then it was taken from me." I would have a greater claim
on the seller if he sold me the land and then it
was taken to pay off a debt—not a debt of mine, a
debt of his. Okay. So that's why you would write מכר mecher
even in a מתנה. matanah. Of course, the obvious question is: How
do we know which way to interpret it? Like if a מכר
mecher needs money to change hands and a מתנה matanah doesn't, so
how do we know when a שטר shtar says מכר, mecher, why
should we assume it's a מתנה matanah but it's just saying this
to give him more rights? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says that we're
talking that the שטר shtar said actually both. It's one שטר. shtar.
The שטר shtar said שדי נתונה לך, sadi netunah lakh, שדי מכורה
לך. sadi mekhura lakh. And when it says both, then we'll assume
it's a מתנה matanah with extra rights. It's given to you as
a מתנה—or matanah it doesn't really matter the order—שדי מכורה לך, sadi
mekhura lakh, שדי נתונה לך. sadi netunah lakh. Once it has the
language of מתנה, matanah, it works without money changing hands. That's the
power of writing it as a שטר מתנה—there shtar matanah might be
other powers as well—and I added this לשון lashon of מכר mecher
that you can be reimbursed. Okay. So it has the double language,
but we interpret it as a מתנה matanah because that's written in
the שטר shtar itself. תוספות Tosafot suggests another possibility, which is fascinating,
which is—you know you've heard about people keeping two sets of books?
So I write this person two שטרות. shtarot. I write to you
one שטר shtar that says שדי מכורה לך, sadi mekhura lakh, and
I write to you another שטר shtar that says שדי נתונה לך.
sadi netunah lakh. So, and by having both שטרות, shtarot, in circumstances
where it's beneficial to you to claim it was a sale, you
produce the שטר shtar that says it was a
sale. In circumstances where it's beneficial to you to produce the שטר
מתנה, shtar matana, you produce the שטר shtar that says it was
a שטר מתנה. shtar matana. What, for example, would be a case
where it's beneficial to produce that שטר? shtar? So the other thing
that Rashbam of Tosafot mentions is this דינא דבר מצרא. dina de-bar
metzra. When I'm selling my field, I have to give first right
of purchase to my neighbors, to people who have adjoining fields. But
if I'm giving my field away as a gift, then I don't
have to offer them to buy it; I'm trying to give it
as a gift. So I want to give you my field and
I don't want to have to deal with my neighbors. So what
I will do is I will write you two שטרות: shtarot: one
שטר shtar as a gift, so that if they claim, 'Hey, why
didn't you sell to us?' you'll produce that שטר, shtar, and one
שטר shtar as a sale, so if a creditor takes it, I'll
have to reimburse you. Now one wonders why this is legal, right?
There's reasons why there's these different הלכות, halakhot, and you have to
decide which it is. But interestingly, that's what we're talking about. Anyway,
the bottom line of all of this is that that was a
special case that a שטר shtar would work, with a מכר mekher
would work without money changing hands because it either was a field
I was trying to offload or it wasn't really a מכר, mekher,
it was really a מתנה. matana.
But a standard מכר mekher does not work by the שטר shtar
alone; it needs the money to change hands. And therefore you have
to say that when the husband sells to the wife, the money...
we are not going to say he's just trying to get access
to those funds. Because if he was, then there would never have
been a payment, and if there was never been a payment for
the field, the שטר shtar would never have effectuated the transfer. Okay,
and therefore that's why we need to say that he is... that
it is a completely legitimate sale and the funds that were paid
were genuine payments for the field and not just him getting his
hands on it. Okay, so that's that position, that it does work
because we don't say he was just trying to get access to
the funds. Now the גמרא Gemara continues.
מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask on this. לוה מן העבד ושחררו, מן האשה
וגרשה. Lava min ha-eved ve-shihraro, min ha-isha ve-gerasha.
A man borrowed from his slave and then he freed him, or
he borrowed money from his wife and then he divorced her. אין
להם עליו כלום. Ein lahem alav kelum. They cannot... they don't... can't
say, 'Hey, pay us up the debt,' because he can basically say,
you know, come on, what was my slave doing with money that
I didn't own? We say קנה עבד קנה רבו. kana eved kana
rabbo. What was my wife doing with money that wasn't mine? Like,
again, not like it's not possible with a wife, but it's, you
know, most cases I should have had access to those funds. So
I'm going to claim that I never really borrowed it; I was
saying I was borrowing it in order to get access to the
funds. Okay, that's exactly לגלויי זוזי הוא דבעי, le-galuyei zuzei hu de-ba'ei,
and we should... we would be willing to believe him. Now, of
course, that raises important questions: if we're going to be willing to
believe him that when he has... that when he got money from
his wife in the context of a loan that it wasn't really
her money, it was really his, he doesn't own it... does that
mean he can just like take money out of her hands and
claim it's his? You know, or so like what's exactly that story?
Like, don't we assume that it is possible for a wife to
hold onto money that's... you know,
to have money outside of her husband's control? So it could be
here it's a question of like who's מוחזק, muhzak, who's in possession,
and תוספות Tosafot later discusses this. Like sure, if the wife was
holding onto cash and she says that it's her, that, you know,
she has it without her husband having rights to it, we would
believe her. But once her husband gets access to that cash and
then says, 'No, no, no, that money was always mine, she was
just, you know, hiding it from me,' we would then believe him.
He would be מוחזק muhzak and given the fact that there is
most standard cases he does have rights to his wife's property... you
know, we would believe him. Again, it is funny because even if
he has rights to his wife's property, a lot of that is
just he has the right to the פירות, peirot, not the קרן.
keren. Okay, but nevertheless, that's what seems to emerge from this case.
So the גמרא Gemara says, even though it was initially framed as
a loan, we're going to now believe him to say it was
always my property. So the גמרא Gemara says,
מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? לאו משום דאמרינן, Lav mishum
de-amrinan, isn't it because we say לגלויי זוזי הוא דבעי? le-galuyei zuzei
hu de-ba'ei? He's just really trying to get access to those funds
and that we should believe him that it's his money even if
it was claimed to be a loan? So that seems to be
a very good parallel argument to the case by the מכר, mekher,
and we should say it wasn't really a good מכר, mekher, he
was just trying to get access to the funds. So the גמרא
Gemara says, שאני התם, Shani hatam, there it's different. דלא ניחא ליה
לשוויי נפשיה עבד לו ולאישה מלכתא. de-la niha lei le-shavyei nafshei eved
lo u-le-isha malketa. A normal person doesn't want to be indebted to
somebody else. So when you piece together, you know, you're considered to
be enslaved to the person you're indebted to. So when you piece
together the various things: number one, it's his literal slave, or it's
his wife, cases where either he definitely owns that money we should
assume by the slave, or there's a reasonable case that he should
have rights to those funds. And the way he got access was
by borrowing,
well, you know, normal people of course, you know, there's a good
reason people could borrow, like he's hard up for funds and his
wife has money. But since... But since we're going to say that
normal people would never want to be indebted, we're going to say
the more reasonable explanation here is not that he's indebted himself, but
the more reasonable explanation is he was just trying to use this
as an excuse to gain access. But when you sell something, you're
not indebting yourself, you're
exchanging like for like, something of one value for something of equal
value, for the money that's worth. So in that type of a
case, it's completely reasonable to think that he was willing to do
an equal exchange. It's not unlikely that people will borrow money, again,
in a commercial society people borrow money all the time for business
reasons, but in a non-commercial society, right, that's why the Torah prohibits,
annuls debt and prohibits interest, etc. That's a very difficult position to
be in. But sale, that's a normal thing. So therefore, we should
say that in that case it's genuine and it's not just to
get access to the funds and he's not believed to say that
those were always his money. Okay, so now we've got
affirming on this entire עמוד amud the position that it is a
good sale and even
though we don't think he's just trying to get access to the
funds, and we might say it in a case where he borrows
money but not in other cases. Okay. שלח רב הונא בר אבין.
Shalach Rav Huna bar Avin. So רב הונא בר אבין Rav Huna
bar Avin sent the following משיב, mishiv, okay, to the students in
the
בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. המוכר שדה לאשתו קנתה. Hamocher sadeh l'ishto kansah.
Someone sells a field to his wife, she takes possession, like we've
been saying, ובעל אוכל פירות. u'baal ochel peirot. But here's an interesting
little codicil or an interesting little הערה he'arah that we haven't mentioned.
Fine, she owns the field, what's the הלכה halakha about fields that
she owns? She has title and he gets the benefit, he's אוכל
פירות. ochel peirot. That's נכסי מלוג, nichsei milug, that's the default of
any property that she owns. Okay, fine, that's an interesting thing we
hadn't thought about, but all right, that makes sense. ברם, Bram, now
the message continued and said, however, although that's my position, רבי אבא
ורבי אבהו וכל גדולי הדור אמרי, Rabbi Abba v'Rabbi Abbahu v'chol gedolei
hador amri, Rabbi Abba and Rabbi Abbahu and all of the greats
of the generation said, so I'm like, which is a little interesting,
I'm a minority position, all of these greats disagreed with me, and
they said: במתנה ביקש ליתנה לה ולמה כתב לה לשום מכר או
לשום מכר כדי ליפות את כוחה. b'matanah bikeshi litno lah v'lamah katav
lo l'shum mechar or l'shum mechar kedei l'yaphot et kocha. He really
wants to give it to her as a gift, he wrote it
as a sale to give her more power. What does that mean?
Okay, it means that he, this is going even further than we
imagined. We were having two possibilities until now. One is it's a
good sale, it's a real מכר, mechar, and now the consequence is
he's אוכל פירות. ochel peirot. Or the other possibility, it wasn't a
sale at all, he just wanted access to the funds. Now we're
going to do a third possibility. Even though he wrote it as
a מכר, mechar, he wanted to give it as a מתנה. matanah.
He wrote a מכר mechar because as we see before, מכר mechar
has greater rights, if it's taken by a creditor, she can ask
to be reimbursed. But we're going to interpret it as a מתנה.
matanah. Now what's the relevance of interpreting it a מתנה? matanah? That
gives her even more rights in a certain way, which is why,
if a husband gives his wife a gift, or somebody, then that
gift is, the implication is because it's being, he's giving it to
her without anything in exchange, that he wants her to have it
free and clear. He wants to completely own it, which means he
is not even אוכל פירות. ochel peirot. So if he gives his
wife this gift of a field, not only does she own it,
she owns it and unlike all other property that she owns, he
has no rights to its benefits, he is not אוכל פירות. ochel
peirot. Okay, so that's like three possibilities when he sells her a
field. One is it wasn't a sale, he was just getting access
to her funds, he keeps the money and the field. The other
is the normal thing, it was a sale, he keeps the money,
she gets the field, but he's אוכל פירות. ochel peirot. The third
possibility is that it was even, it was the best for her,
it was a sale, it was valid, but it was also really
done as a מתנה, matanah, and because it was done as a
מתנה matanah he's not even אוכל פירות. ochel peirot. Now תוספות Tosafot
makes an ingenious claim, or a statement interpretation,
and he says: I'm going to tell you why it was a
מתנה. matanah. Because you remember before that the גמרא Gemara suggested maybe
he was really just trying to get access to the funds, but
shouldn't the שטר shtar work by itself? Okay, and they said: no,
a שטר מכר shtar mechar needs funds as well, and they said:
but a שטר מתנה shtar matanah wouldn't need funds. So here תוספות
Tosafot is saying is, here actually is the a possible logical conclusion
from those statements. We say he was just trying to get access
to the funds, so fine, he keeps the money. He keeps the
money because it wasn't a real sale, he was just getting access
to the funds and we're going to believe him that it was
always his money. But there was also a שטר, shtar, and the
שטר shtar might have said מכר, mechar, but we've seen before... that
sometimes a שטר shtar can say מכר mecher and be a שטר
מתנה. shtar matana. So therefore this שטר, shtar, forget the money, that's
his. This שטר, shtar, we're going to read this שטר מכר shtar
mecher as a שטר מתנה shtar matana and the field is hers
and because it's hers as a מתנה, matana, she gets to keep
the fruit and he doesn't eat the fruit. So one possible conclusion
from saying there's two ways of interpreting, we're going to say that
he was just getting access to the funds. One is he was
getting access to the funds and the whole thing is void and
he keeps the money and the field, and the other is the
diametric opposite: he was just getting access to the funds, he keeps
the money, but the שטר shtar is still a real שטר, shtar,
a valid שטר, shtar, and fundamentally not a שטר מכר shtar mecher
but a שטר מתנה, shtar matana, and therefore she keeps the field
and he's not אוכל פירות. ochel peiros. So we have three very
nice possibilities here of how to interpret what happened. Okay, let's go
on. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, מיתיבי, meivei, I'll ask you on this. לווה מן העבד loveh
min ha'eved according to the position that it was good and that
he wasn't just trying to get access to the funds and it
was a good מכר, mecher, it was a standard מכר, mecher, it's
her field and he's אוכל פירות. ochel peiros. One minute, again the
same question.
לווה מן העבד ושחררו מן האשה וגרשה אין להם אלא כלום, loveh
min ha'eved veshichrero min ha'isha vegeirasho ein lahem ela kelum, he borrows
from his wife and divorces her, he doesn't really owe her any
money. So is it מאי טעמא לאו משום דאמרינן לגילויי זוזי הוא
דבעי, mai ta'ama lav mishum de'amrinan legiluyei zuzei hu deba'ei, isn't it
because we say even though it was a loan, we're going to
interpret it as he was just getting access to her funds? גמרא
Gemara says no, and therefore here too, and it should not be
a מכר. mecher. גמרא Gemara says no, שאני התם דלא לישווי נפשיה
עבדא ולא לישווי נפשיה מלווה, shani hasam delo lishvei nafshai avda velo
lishvei nafshai malva, no, no, no, no. There we're going to be
more inclined to interpret it that way because normal people would not
want to become a debtor. Okay, but in this case where you're
not making yourself a debtor, we're going to interpret it as a
legitimate sale. So we've got the idea that it is possible when
money changes hands between husband and wife, we're going to see it
as he's really just trying to use this as a ruse to
get access to her funds which he is claiming that he is
entitled to, not that it's not possible that it's her, but that
now that he's got access to them he's going to claim it
was always his and we'll believe him. That's maybe in a case
of borrowing money. But in a case of a sale, we're going
to believe it was a legitimate sale and that's where all of
the opinions here have been saying and that therefore she is אוכל
פירות, ochel peiros, it's a legitimate sale she owns the field and
if it's a sale, he's אוכל פירות, ochel peiros, but maybe we'll
interpret it even more as a מתנה matana and then she'll be
אוכל פירות. ochel peiros. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר
רב, amar Rav, now we're going to come to a conclusion: המוכר
שדה לאשתו קנתה והבעל אוכל פירות. hamocher sadeh le'ishto kansah vehaba'al ochel
peiros. If you sell it, then that's a normal, a husband sells
to his wife, it's a normal sale, she owns it and the
husband gets the fruit. במתנה, bematana, and if he gives it as
a gift to her, קנתה ואין הבעל אוכל פירות. kansah ve'ein haba'al
ochel peiros. She gets it and he doesn't eat the fruit. So
that was what was underlying the earlier statement and here we're just
saying it very plain and simple. Sale, normal sale, none of this
other fancy stuff. Okay, it's not just to get the funds and
whatever, and the consequence, he's אוכל פירות ochel peiros like any other
property. A gift, he's not אוכל פירות. ochel peiros.
She owns it completely. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rebbe Eliezer omer, רבי אליעזר
Rebbe Eliezer says, אחד זה ואחד זה קנתה ואין הבעל אוכל פירות.
echad zeh ve'echad zeh kansah ve'ein haba'al ochel peiros. That even in
the case of מכר, mecher, the husband does not eat פירות, peiros,
like the opinion at the top of the דף daf of רבי
אבא Rebbe Abba and רבי אבהו Rebbe Abbahu and וכל גדולי הדור,
vekol gedolei hador, presumably because we say that even if it's framed
as a מכר, mecher, because it's to his wife he really is
giving it to his wife and he wants her to own it
free and clear, and maybe because of that interesting approach תוספות Tosafos
said that the money was for him to get access to the
money, the transfer of the field is a straight מתנה. matana. Okay,
so what is the conclusion of all of this? ואין הבעל אוכל
פירות. ve'ein haba'al ochel peiros. Okay, אחד זה ואחד זה קנתה ואין
הבעל אוכל פירות. echad zeh ve'echad zeh kansah ve'ein haba'al ochel peiros.
עבד רב חסדא עובדא כרבי אליעזר. avad Rav Chisda uvda keRebbe Eliezer.
So רב חסדא Rav Chisda did like רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer and
said that in a case of money, the בעל ba'al was not
אוכל פירות ochel peiros like רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer and against רב.
Rav. So אמר ליה רבי נחוקבא ורבי נחמיה בני בנתיה דרב, amar
lei Rebbe Nachukva veRebbe Nechemiah banei banteih deRav, so these two rabbis,
רב'ס Rav's grandsons, took offense that he paskened against רב. Rav. רב
Rav says that if it's a מכר mecher the בעל ba'al is
אוכל פירות ochel peiros and he treated it as a מתנה, matana,
as a gift, and said the husband wasn't אוכל פירות. ochel peiros.
So they said to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, שביק מר רב רבוי
ועביד כזוטרי? shavik mar rav revvei ve'avid kezutrei? You're abandoning the great
opinions, the opinions of the great ones, of רב, Rav, and you're
paskening like these minor authorities to treat this as a מתנה matana
even when it was done as a sale? So he said, אמר
ליה אנא נמי כרב רבוי עבדי, amar lei ana nami keRav revvei
avdi, I've got great authorities that I also rely on. Who is
that? דכי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן, dechi ata Ravin amar Rebbe
Yochanan, רבין Ravin said in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rebbe Yochanan,
who was a colleague of רב. Rav. רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer was
like, you know, one generation, a student of רבי יוחנן. Rebbe Yochanan.
But I have a teaching in the name of רבי יוחנן Rebbe
Yochanan who was a colleague of רב: Rav: אחד זה ואחד זה
קנתה ואין הבעל אוכל פירות. echad zeh ve'echad zeh kansah ve'ein haba'al
ochel peiros. Whether as a sale, whether as a gift, she owns
it fully and the husband does not אוכל פירות. ochel peiros. So
it's interesting. So it's interesting, a סוגיא sugia that began totally to
sort of negate the sale and again, I want to say it's
not about saving the husband, saving the wife, we were willing to
say before that what were we suggesting, in the end we didn't
say it, but we thought for a while when a wife would
sell to a husband, we would say that was really void too,
she didn't really mean to sell it to him. Here we were
starting by saying when a husband sells to a wife, that's void
and he keeps the money. Okay, but in the end we say
no, it is a מכר mecher and not only is it a
מכר, mecher, but now we're even it seems to be putting forward
positions that it's a מכר mecher that he's not even אוכל פירות,
ochel peirot, it's a מכר mecher like a מתנה matana that she
gets to keep all of the benefits. Okay, now what is the
הלכה? halacha? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so says Rava, הלכתא hilchata the
הלכה halacha is המוכר שדה לאשתו לא קנתה. hamocher sadeh le'ishto lo
kanta. Again,
against everything we've been saying, which is shocking. All of the emphasis
has been that it's a legitimate sale. And he says no, it's
not a legitimate sale. He was only trying to get access to
the funds. והבעל אוכל פירות ve-ha-ba'al ochel peirot and the husband eats
the fruit, which is like what? If it's not a sale, it's
still his property. הא בעל אוכל פירות ha ba'al ochel peirot as
if it is a good sale. So we'll see in a minute
about that. Let's hold on. במתנה קנתה ואין הבעל אוכל פירות. bematana
kanta ve'ein ha-ba'al ochel peirot. So if it's a straight gift, nobody
disagrees. She has it completely, the husband is not אוכל פירות. ochel
peirot. But what about the issue that we've been debating, which is
מכר? mecher? And until now we've only suggested the we've only really
put forth the position that it's good and now he's saying it's
no good. Okay, but then side by side he says it is
good. So which is it? So the גמרא Gemara is let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
So the גמרא Gemara says תרתי? tartei? How can you say both?
In a case when it's a מכר mecher that both it's not
good and it's good and he's eating the פירות. peirot. So the
גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. כאן במעות
טמונים כאן במעות שאינם טמונים. kan be-ma'ot tmunim kan be-ma'ot she-einam tmunim.
Ah, finally that makes sense, the circumstances matter. Where was she drawing
the funds from? Was she drawing the funds from an account that
everybody knew about? Then it's a standard good sale and the husband
is אוכל פירות ochel peirot like any normal sale. Okay, we don't
make it into a מתנה. matana.
But if she took the funds from an account that was hidden,
okay, and she you know, then and again I don't know, what
would be the default? I assume, I don't know who has the
burden of proof here, okay, but I would assume the burden of
proof would I don't know how do you prove the fact that
something was hidden? So I don't exactly know like where's the burden
of proof? But anyway, if it was from money that was hidden,
then we will say, ah, then you add that to it, we're
going to say he's only trying to get access to the funds
because we've seen that by the case of borrowing money, that's how
we interpret it. So here too, when the evidence points to that,
that it was from hidden funds, then we're going to say it's
not a real sale. דאמר רב יהודה מעות טמונים לא קנתה. de-amar
Rav Yehuda ma'ot tmunim lo kanta. If it's
from hidden funds, it's not good. Again, I don't know who has
the burden of proof and how you prove it. מעות שאינם טמונים
קנתה, ma'ot she-einam tmunim kanta, but if it was a known account,
it is then it is good. Okay, so מתנה matana she owns
it, he's not אוכל פירות. ochel peirot.
We had by the case of a מכר mecher three possibilities. One
which we had until this last line been discounting, that it's completely
void,
that he was only trying to get access to the funds. The
middle one that it's legitimate and it's like a normal מכר. mecher.
And the third one, which is that even though it's looked as
a מכר, mecher, you know, maybe he was getting access to the
funds, but maybe the other part of it is a מתנה matana
and she gets to keep all of the benefits. And in the
end we say no, that first possibility that we had been bracketing,
that would be true in a case when she was drawing on
hidden funds. And if it was not drawn on hidden funds, then
it would be a straight-up מכר, mecher, she would own it and
he would be אוכל פירות. ochel peirot. Okay, so that was very
interesting in terms of understanding how to interpret it, but also in
terms of sort of seeing these dynamics that when a husband has
a lot of rights to his wife's property, but not absolute. Some
property she's אוכל פירות, ochel peirot, a lot most property she has
title and he's not אוכל פירות. ochel peirot. How do we view
it when he's doing things and getting access to her property? And
some cases, certainly like a case of borrowing money, we're going to
believe him to say that this was always his money that he
was hiding from him. Yeah, it was money she earned on side
jobs that she never told me about and that she hid away
and we would believe him. With that in mind, let's take a
look at the next little piece in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. אין מקבלין פקדונות לא מן הנשים ולא מן העבדים.
ein mikablin pikdonot lo min ha-nashim ve-lo min ha-avadim.
You do not accept holding something, right, as a to safeguard something
for somebody from a woman or from a wife, I should say,
or from a slave. Why? Because you're afraid that they're giving you
property that isn't theirs. You know, the slave stole something from the
master's house and is giving it to you. The wife took something
that was money she should have been reporting to her husband. You
are the hidden funds, you're the Swiss bank account. She earned this
money and she's asking you to hold on to it. You're afraid
that might be the case, so therefore you don't want to be
a party to that. You don't want to be holding onto funds
that might not be belonging to that person. So you don't accept
it. Okay?
ומן התינוקות u'min hatinokot and not from kids also because generally stuff
that kids have is their parents', you know, they took something from
their parents' house. Hi, Mr., will you hold on to this wallet
for me, you know, or so obviously sometimes the circumstances are more
obvious, but you know, what are kids doing with money, or what
are kids doing with valuable objects? Maybe they just took it from
their parents' house and they're using you as the way to hide
it away from their parents. So you do not, you should not
accept them. קיבל מן האשה, kibal min ha'isha, now if you did
go ahead and you did agree to take it from the wife,
יחזיר לאשה, yachzir la'isha, then give it back to her. Don't say,
oh, I'm going to assume it was her husband's, I'm going to
give it back to her husband. Meaning, you don't want to be
sort of, you know, drawn into this possibility and then be playing
this unwitting role in secreting away funds from somebody. But you don't
know, that's just a suspicion, right? You should at the end of
the day, you know, give people, you know, the presumption that people
are acting honestly. So therefore, if you did accept it, then you're
going to assume that it was hers and you're going to give
it back to her. Okay? יחזיר לאשה. yachzir la'isha. ואם מתה יחזיר
לבעלה. ve'im meta yachzir le'ba'alah. Now if she however dies, then you
give back to the husband. Why? Because even if it was hers,
once a woman dies, her husband inherits her. Okay? So obviously if
you do accept it, you will believe it's hers, but you shouldn't
accept it because there's the possibility something else is going on. קיבל
מן העבד, kibal min ha'eved, יחזיר לעבד. yachzir le'eved. Now if you
got it from the slave, return to the slave. Now that's a
very hard idea to understand
because how—the wife we've been discussing various ways in which she owns
property that's not her husband's, but the slave, you know, מה שקנה
עבד קנה רבו, ma shekaneh eved kaneh rabo, you know, בעלו, ba'alo,
בעלו, ba'alo,
which is because you know the slave's hand is like the master's
hand and it goes straight to the master. Now it is possible
to give a slave a property on the condition that it does
not transfer to the master. So there is a small possibility that
the slave still, you know, actually does own this himself. So maybe
that's what this is about. Or the other possibility, the רשב"ם Rashbam
doesn't discuss this, but the other possibility that occurs to me is
is that, you know, maybe the slave gave it to
you—it depends, like did he say hold this, this is mine, or
did he just say can you watch this? And maybe if he
says can you watch this, maybe he's doing it to you on
the behest of his master. So therefore, the same way you basically
were willing to accept this from him and believe that his master
had entrusted him with, you know, with sort of taking care of
this object and making sure that it was taken care of, then
you should be willing to on the same virtue that you took
it from him, you should be willing to give it back to
him and assume that, no no, I'm only going to give it
back to your master. Why? Like if you believed me to hold
on to it that I was operating on behalf of my master,
you should also believe me to give it back to me that
I'll give it back to my master. So could be that's why
you give it back to the slave, not because what do you
call it, not because you believe it's his, but just because you
believe he's he's doing it for the sake of his master.
ואם מת יחזיר לרבו. ve'im met yachzir lerabo. But if the slave
is dead, you give back to the master because obviously you were
all along assuming it was the property of the master. Now by
the way, the רשב"ם Rashbam says that this would be true even
if the slave was freed, because fundamentally in this case you really
never believed it was his. So when you gave it back to
him, you were giving back to him again presumably because he was
acting on his master's behalf. But if he was—but if he gave
it to you and then was freed and then he, I don't
know, asked for it back or he died, then in that case
you wouldn't give—whatever, you wouldn't give it to him, you wouldn't give
it to his heirs. According to the רשב"ם, Rashbam, you always believed
it was his master's and you'd give it back to his master.
As opposed to the case by the wife, that if she gave
it to you and then she was divorced, you would—and then she
died, you would give it to her heirs, you would not give
it to the husband. Because in the case of the wife, you
don't want to possibly be party to her secreting funds that are
of her husband's away from her husband, but once you've accepted them,
you believe that they were her funds. Okay? And that's why you
would always give it back, you know, to her or to her
heirs. If she's still married, her heirs are her husband. Okay. Now,
קיבל מן הקטן, kibal min hakatan, what if you took it from
a minor? So in that case, you don't give it back to
the minor because you're afraid that it might genuinely be his—for, you
know, there's ways like, for example, if somebody—you know, cases where a
minor can earn stuff or a מציאה metzia or whatever the case
might be. Okay? But you don't want to give it back to
him because then you're being irresponsible with it. You're there as a
guardian and you're giving it to a minor. It's ironic, but the
owner who will not be—will not keep it protected. So you have
to make sure that this object, which you have a—you have a
duty of protecting, is actually—a duty of care—that you're actually caring for
it. So part of caring for it is not giving it back
to the minor. So יעשה לו סגולה, ya'aseh lo segula, you do
a סגולה. segula. which we'll see what that means is basically you
invest it and you protect it until you give it back to
him when he's an adult.
דמת יחזיר ליורשיו. d'meis yachzir leyorshav. And if the minor dies, you
give back to whoever the minor's heirs are, obviously not his sons,
but brothers, uncles, father, whatever. So again, like the case by the
woman, you believe, although you don't want to be party to something
nefarious and therefore you try and you don't accept it to begin
with, if you accept it, you believe it was the minor's. Now,
וכולן שאמרו בשעת מיתתן, vechullan she'ameru bishat mitatan, as for any of
them say when they're dying, של פלוני הם, shel ploni heim, יעשה
כפירושן. ya'aseh k'peirushan. I don't know if this וכולן vechullan applies to
the case of עבד eved because again, but who knows. Anyway, but
certainly in the case of the wife and the minor, if when
they're dying they said, 'you know what, this wasn't mine and it
wasn't my husband's, I was really holding on to this for somebody
else,' and here I am. But if they're not dying, they'll just
say give it back, you know, 'why are you telling me to
give it to this person? Here, I'll give it back to you,
you give it to that person.' But they're dying and therefore they
don't have an opportunity to do it, and they say, 'you know
what, that thing I gave you to watch for me, that wasn't
mine, it wasn't my husband's, it belonged to ראובן, Reuven, give it
to ראובן.' Reuven. So in that case, we'll believe them because the
same way I would have assumed it was the wife's and given
it back to her, I'll believe her when she says it belongs
to ראובן. Reuven. ואם לאו, ve'im lav, now, but if not. Now
what does 'if not' mean? Now it could 'if not' could mean
like, if what she says doesn't make sense. She said, 'go give
it to ראובן Reuven who lives at, you know, 100 Main Street,'
and there's no ראובן Reuven who lives on 100 Main Street. So
then, יעשה פירוש לפירושן, ya'aseh peirush l'peirushan, you try to reinterpret what
they're saying to make sense of it. That's one way to interpret.
But what we're going to see that the גמרא's Gemara going to
say it means is, if you don't believe them, if you suspect
that it really never was hers or really never was ראובן's Reuven
and she's just סתם stam saying it, then find a way to
reinterpret what she's saying in order to give it back to her
husband. Okay, so we're never, like we're still considering the possibility that
it was never hers to begin with. So what does that mean?
So we're going to have a case that's going to illustrate that.
דבתיה דרבה בר בר חנה, devatya derabba bar bar channah, the wife
of רבה בר בר חנה, Rabba Bar Bar Channah, כי שכיבא, ki
shechiva, when she was dying, אמרה, amrah, she said, הני כיפי דמרתא
ובני ברתא. hanni kifi demarta u'vnei barta. These are like, what do
you call it,
bracelets or whatever, or rings, you know, that I'm holding on to,
they actually belong to מרתא Marta and his and his grandsons, the
sons of his daughter. אתו לקמיה דרב, atu lekamei derav, they came
up to רב Rav and they said, 'should we believe her?' Because
you know, otherwise we would have assumed that they were hers and
that her husband would inherit
her. So anyway, by the way, this is interesting because this isn't
even that they're being held by a third party, right? This is
just like סתם, stam, it sounds like she was holding on to
them, and this is what she said, you know, you should do
with them. Okay, so should we listen to her or not? So
אמר להו amar lehu אי מהימנא לכו i meheimna lacho עבידו כפירושה.
avidu k'peirushah. If you trust her, יעשה כפירושה. ya'aseh k'peirushah. If you
trust her that they really, you know, in general you trust her,
you assume that, you know, I guess the husband trusts, I don't
know who's trusting her, you, the, the rabbi, he's deciding the case,
you the husband trusts her.
I mean the רשב"א Rashba says שלא גנבה ממך כלום, shelo ganva
mimcha klum, you the husband trust her. Okay, so he's now speaking
to the husband and saying, 'if you trust her that she doesn't
steal from you and that, you know, she's not hiding away any
funds from you, and therefore if she's holding on to something, either
it's genuinely hers or she's genuinely holding on to it for somebody
else, then do what she says, and then give it to whoever
she claims it belongs to because you trust her.' ואם לאו, ve'im
lav, but אמר להו amar lehu
אי מהימנא לכו i meheimna lacho עבידו כפירושה avidu k'peirushah ואם לא
ve'im lo עשה פירוש לפירושה. asah peirush l'peirushah. But if you don't
believe her, that maybe you suspect that she was hiding funds from
you,
then in that case, you know, or you specifically don't believe that
it belongs to this מרתא, Marta, but maybe more generally you're you
you you're you you suspect that that this she might have been
hiding away stuff for hiding stuff from you, then find a way
to reinterpret what she says so that ultimately, you know, you can
take possession of them.
ואיכא דאמרי הכי אמר להו, v'ika d'amri hachi amar lehu, אמידה לכו
amida lacho עשה כפירושה. asah k'peirushah. If it's a, you know,
you know, if it's sort of like determined for you, like if
you know, you assess it this way, if you assess that those
people, the בני ברתא, bnei barta, are people that actually could have
these jewelry and it makes sense, you know, so it's not a
general question of whether you believe her or not, but if you
know if what she's claiming makes sense and it fits, then do
what she's saying. Okay, or another interpretation is like, you know, like
if you know that they're people that really would give things to
your wife to watch for them. So if in this particular circumstance
this makes sense, then יעשה כפירושה, ya'aseh k'peirushah, do what she's saying.
So if what she says, if no, and no, עשה פירוש לפירושה
asay peirush l'peirusha find a way to reinterpret what she's saying. So
again, what's fascinating here is the woman is in possession of something,
okay, and there is this still this like little suspicion that because
the husband is supposed to have access to his wife's funds, right,
maybe they're really the husband's and she's hiding it from the husband.
So that's why in one case we would say that maybe a
sale isn't a sale, he was trying to get access, in the
end we didn't say that, we said a loan isn't a loan,
he was trying to get access, but a sale is unless it's
from hidden funds. But we also would say a third party couldn't
accept something because maybe that's a possibility. And in this case, right,
if the wife dies and there was stuff that she was had
somebody watching for her, stuff that was under her control, then we
also raise this possibility that says maybe it was also the husband's
funds, and it's actually interesting, it seems like we allow the husband
to decide whether you think this makes sense or not or in
general you trust her and if he thinks that it doesn't then
we're going to assume that it was his funds that he was
hiding away. You know, that leads תוספות Tosafot to some interesting speculation.
Let's say the husband went and grabbed money out of his wife's
hands and claimed that this was always his funds, you know, that
she was hiding it from him, would we believe him or not?
You know, and he has different opinions based on sort of the
different ideas that came up in the גמרא. Gemara. So it's quite
sort of fascinating how we deal with this as, you know, it's
clear, you know, this possibility which was present, you know, in a
case where the husband had rights to the funds, the wife could
have earnings herself, you know, that he had rights to, but there
was ways in which the wife had property he didn't have rights
to, and therefore what do we do with that possibility, which cases
do we interpret in favor of the wife and in favor of
the husband? Okay, so to be continued tomorrow.
Stay safe and inside and warm everybody.